all right hello and welcome everyone
it's march 17th 2022 we're here in actin
flab live stream number 40.1 discussing
a free energy principle for generic
quantum systems
welcome to the actin flap
we're a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here all qrf
and video etiquette for live stream will
be hopefully following
to learn more about active lab head over
to activeinference.org
and for the rest of active stream 40.1
um blue thanks for being the facilitator
sure so in this stream today our goal is
to learn and discuss this paper a free
energy principle for generic quantum
systems by chris fields carl christian
james blazebrook and michael levin and
we have both chris and carl on the
stream with us today
so if we maybe want to just start off
briefly with doing
some introductions so my name is blue
knight i'm an independent researcher in
new mexico and i will pass it off to the
first author prince
um hi good morning and uh thanks for
attending this
discussion
uh this is a
a paper about
active inference um
and how to place the active entrance
framework in a quantum information
theoretic setting
so
what i
thought i should do to introduce it is
just give a little bit of the motivation
for doing that
quantum information theory
is an outgrowth of
quantum theory that started in the 70s
or or even you could take it back to the
60s if you wanted to
and its goal was to consider physical
interactions as information exchange
processes
and to reformulate quantum theory in
this way
and so
it has a very natural kind of overlap
with what
carl has been doing with the free energy
principle in terms of of reformulating
physics
essentially all of physics and
information
and decision theoretic terms
so why why quantum theory why go to
this theory that's often thought of as a
theory only of very
tiny objects that are moving very fast
and the reason is that it's scale free
and
conceptually
quantum theory is very simple
and
it
has one
core hypothesis which is the print the
principle of unitarity
and the principle of unitarity is simply
the idea that total information is
conserved
so quantum theory is based on a
conservation law a proposed conservation
law conservation of information
so what
going to quantum theory really
forces us to do
is to take
seriously the project that
um
carl spent a lot of time on
in his uh
particular physics paper in 2019
which is to understand what we mean
when we say that we've observed a system
multiple times
what we mean when we say we've
interacted with the same object
multiple times
and
it forces us to
uh or at least it encourages us to take
that question seriously and it provides
a number of tools for talking about that
question
and we'll talk about that as we get into
the
paper
but um and that's in a sense our
motivation it's to take this
um
very nice
quite abstract
uh
but in a sense very fundamental
toolkit
that's based around the idea of
conservation of information and
apply it to this question of of active
inference
so i'll let
carl pick it up from there
nice well thank you it's a great
pleasure to be here i have to say i was
hoping to learn more
a great opportunity from my point of
view just to
hear a conversation and probably
participate in terms of how this sport
run and control scale free
background free and that's what i think
is one of the
the most
attractive
um parsimonious um
benefits of taking a quantum perspective
on this it reminds me of the queenian
desert landscape a minimal assumption
which which
i'm always drawn to and apply this to
some fundamental questions which have
actually been beautifully listed for us
at the top here
about things and crucially um
how things
coupled to other things in terms of
measurement and observation and
inference
so
i'm personally delighted and hungry to
learn about
how
simple questions about the nature of
things
um we observe and pleasure and make
imprints about
can be cast that was fundamental in this
fundamental or from this fundamental
perspective of quantum information
very nice thank you
james thanks for joining us would you
like to introduce yourself and maybe say
a few words about the paper or pick it
up from there
oh um
hello
um
you may call me jim
thank you um
um
you are
you you you want a potted biography do
you
um anyway um i'm a retired academic um
emeritus professor of eastern illinois
university and adjunct
associate professor
the university of illinois at
urbana-champaign
um
my background is
global analytic
geometry and some related areas but in
the last uh 16 or 17 years i've been
um
applying mathematical techniques to
cognitive neuroscience and
foundations of
quantum biology and more recently
quantum information as as it
relates to the free energy principle
great thank you
uh stephen do you want to maybe
introduce yourself and give a thought
about the paper something you like or
remembered or curious about today
yeah thank you hi i'm stephen i'm i'm
based in toronto
i'm just doing a practice-based phd into
social topographies and community
development
and i have got backgrounds many years
ago in chemistry
and i'm i'm really curious about um
the way that this idea of something
that's scale free
uh also ties to something which seems to
be very specific
on scale i
wear something that's highly contextual
and highly uh
bounded by degrees of freedom at a
certain scale
and then how something could be inferred
that's
across all sorts of scales so that
that's really something i'm curious
about on this particular piece of
great work daniel do you have any other
like particular questions that you want
to address or
just looking forward to
seeing the discussion and anyone who's
watching live can ask a question so i'm
curious about how
also like steven said the specificity
of a given experiment
interfaces with general
aspects of the formalism and uh
many other things but
we'll go go ahead blue
well do we want to maybe start there do
you guys want to speak to that
scale deterministic
aspect of the quantum fep
well i can say something here
um
in
any information theory
will start with some state space so some
set of degrees of freedom that have some
set of values
and in the paper we restrict ourselves
to finite state spaces because we're
really interested in systems that only
have access to finite energy
and so finite computational resources
so one starts with a state
space and in a sense that
state space
when viewed from kind of the external
perspective of the theorist who's
defining it sets the scale of the
problem
because in defining the state space
you're saying what the values are of the
degrees of freedom
and
when you say
what are the possible values
you are implicitly making some
assumptions about resolution
so
uh and making some assumptions about
measurement
so for example if we think of a
canonical quantum system which is a
cubit just one
a particle with a spin
uh and we say the spin can be up or down
um
then we made an assumption about how how
we can measure the spin
and
the most natural mathematical framework
is a three-dimensional
ball of values or sphere of values if
you normalize them
and that's making an assumption that we
can measure the spin
in any one of three directions
um
and so
here we
have imposed some possible values on
this on this
set of degrees of freedom
and so in a sense we've set a scale for
the problem
similarly if we're talking about
uh interactions between human beings
uh clearly there are lots and lots of
degrees of freedom that we can think of
but we typically think about only a tiny
handful of degrees of freedom
that have to do for example with verbal
communication or visual communication
olfactory communication or some other
kind of communication
and we always impose
resolution restrictions we can say this
difference is detectable
and these other differences aren't
detectable
and whenever we make a decision like
that we're setting a scale
and when we characterize the information
theory is scale-free
we're just saying that the formalism
doesn't change when the scale changes
so the formalism the
mathematical
description
remains exactly the same
regardless of what
scales we pick by choosing the possible
values of the degrees of freedom that
we're talking about we don't change
anything else about the way the theory
works
so that's that's all that's skill-free
means it it doesn't mean that we've
somehow abolished the notion of scale
uh
that's part of our experience
um
so it's not something we're going to
make go away
it's that we haven't changed the way the
math works depending on the notion of
scale
and you know the most the most notorious
example of that
uh thing that we're not doing
is
the
historical division of the world into
kind of a quantum domain a classical
domain in a cosmological domain
where you use three entirely different
theories
right quantum theory classical physics
and general relativity
to talk about what's going on so that's
not scale free
there you're you're radically altering
the mathematical description
to deal with different kinds of problems
so that's what we're not doing trying to
use the same mathematical description
uh to deal with all problems
i think that's a really helpful
description chris because so many times
when we think about quantum we think
about the very very very small like
subatomic particles and so it's pretty
amazing to see
math that's interchangeable with my
level of existence like not just tiny
little pieces of me um being used from
quantum theory
what um
is there any other math that you know of
or any other
um
examples of
math that's been interchangeable with
like classical and cosmological and
quantum scales ever before or is this
maybe the first time that's ever been
done
oh well
no if you look if you look back to
classical physics in the era of newton
or
even i think the better representative
is is classical physics is reformulated
by laplace
um
in that era electromagnetism wasn't
really understood yet so people were
thinking about classical physics in
terms of
mechanical interactions and gravity
um
but the idea at that point
was that
forces act instantaneously
and
forces uh
act with one over r squared dependence
that was the only force that was really
understood the force of gravity
uh
forces were symmetrical
right newton's second law action and
reaction
and
this theory was meant to be universal
so if you look at the structure of that
theory
as various people have pointed out i
think nicholas guyson has written a
couple of papers about this
it's a non-local theory
and even even in laplace's era
they realized that there was a a deep
issue with this theory that you know if
a
rock rolls downhill on the moon then
that immediately affects the state of
everything on earth it in fact
immediately affects the state of
everything in the universe
so that starts to look a lot like
entanglement
that states are not locally independent
um
and that's that's the fundamental thing
that einstein attacked about classical
physics in formulating
uh
the theory of relativity was to
insist on
uh
non-instantaneous forces which just
means forces transmitted by some carrier
which we call light
uh but light is really just a carrier of
information it could have been anything
it could have been neutrinos or
something like that
um
so
what einstein did that was most
revolutionary was to impose locality on
physics
and
that
in a sense divided the world into realms
that from a formal perspective not just
a practical perspective
could be treated independently
and so it's no surprise that einstein
hated the idea of entanglement
because entanglement was undoing
precisely what he had done to
in his mind repair physics
so yeah i mean classical physics of the
time of applause was formally a
scale-free theory
that's awesome thank you for uh the
clarification there so einstein einstein
broke physics
uh stephen did you have a question yeah
just one question sort of following from
that is
as someone sort of thinking about how
this might
play out in other
ways is it useful to think about things
all the way up from the smallest
and systems all the way up down from the
biggest and classical as being
where we're trying to
name things as systems
so that
because often i hear people talking
system system systems only but the use
of
things seems to be important
as well and i'm wondering if
we should have more thinness in our
way of looking at the world
oh should i comment on that yeah okay
well
this i think you're raising here a
really interesting question
and
uh when we talk about
things
as as
carl so beautifully emphasized in
his 2019 paper
we are implicitly talking about
something that has an identity
and that maintains that identity through
time
and that's a deep
philosophical assumption that's nearly
always implicit i mean people just don't
talk about that assumption very much
and when we when we use the word system
uh
we're
i think often
trying to speak a lot more loosely
but in fact our language doesn't let us
speak more loosely if i talk about a
system
then implicitly i'm saying
i've got a particular state space
that's what a system is
and
if i
talk about a different state space then
i'm talking about a different system
so
uh
let's apply that to something
interesting like embryology
uh
i pick a set of degrees of freedom that
are meant to be the degrees of freedom
of the zygote
and
uh i then
you know a few days later
have a set of degrees of freedom that
are the degrees of freedom of some kind
of early stage embryo
but i want to say this is the same thing
as the zygote
well i'm now really abusing my notation
right in a really serious way
by
saying that these two are the same thing
even though they have different state
spaces
so
this is a
i think this is a fundamental
question
for
any science that
bases itself on the notion of a state
space
how to talk
about of
moving between
different degrees of freedom and
associating those things
with with some kind of evolution
of a of a kind of meta thing
that we regard as a single entity
and this is this is one reason that uh
at the beginning of this paper we assume
that we have some
single system
that we divide into
we draw a decompositional boundary
and that decompositional boundary is
basically arbitrary
or it's completely arbitrary
but when we're we're doing something
like
embryology
we're looking at a decompositional
boundary between the thing we're
interested in the embryo
and the rest of the universe including
us
that's getting bigger and bigger and
bigger
and
so we need it we need a way to talk
about that sort of thing and we just we
allied that problem in this paper
we we talk about
a fixed decomposition
uh
that that divides the entire universe
into two parts that we can characterize
the interaction between
but but yes underlying all of this is
this much larger question of how we
think about decompositional boundaries
that are expanding
with respect to some parameter that we
call time of course that time
is
not anyone's observable time
because we're we're trying to talk about
it though at the level of the universe
as a whole
so we you can very quickly get into
extremely deep
questions
so two things that um
came up there uh really for me is like
okay yeah you're thinking about the
embryo suddenly that's like a system
that's separate from the world but even
like within the embryo like where do you
draw the line between the placenta and
the embryo and when so so like there's
even some fuzzy blurring um at the
developmental scale
and also really the notion of time and
time irreversibility
and memory and encoding was just
something i found absolutely fascinating
about
this paper so so you mentioned that um
the the quantum the free energy
principle for generic quantum systems
does not imply
like a space
background like it doesn't need a
space-time background to operate but
then like brought time back in in terms
of memory and encoding um and i just
wonder if anybody maybe wants to speak a
little bit more about that or or help us
understand how and why you don't need
space or time for its work
well i could talk about that a little
bit if no one else wants to pick it up
let me go back to the first thing you
said though blue which was about
boundaries and how hard it is for
example to draw boundaries in something
like embryology
there's another deep deep assumption
that we make
that the boundaries that we draw in the
world are somehow ontological
or objective and observer independent
and
quantum theory and and many other
sort of theoretical approaches remind us
constantly that that's a bad assumption
that
uh
drawing thinking of these boundaries as
antic causes all kinds of formal
problems
so for example
the associativity of the state space
multiplication operator becomes invalid
so you can you have to throw out the
whole vector space formalism
oh so i mean real problems
uh
so
so boundaries are observer dependent
in
any formalism like this
so what do we mean by this universal
time
it's a construct
it's it's a theoretical
convenience
and we map it on to our observable time
which is time measured by our clock
and since we're we're the theorists we
can say okay we're going to privilege
our clock
and
we're going to assume that our clock is
somehow universal even though we know
that that doesn't make any sense
and
when we think of space-time i mean the
term background-free comes from
cosmology or quantum cosmology
and
it's the idea that
if we want to
understand
gravity
or if we want to understand space-time
as an emergent phenomenon
then we need a theoretical approach that
doesn't build space-time into it
but if we think of biology
how many organisms what fraction of
organisms have anything like our
experience of space
to what extent
is
space part of
the world of
organisms that we're interested in
and
to what extent is
space as we see it
a construct of our ability to make
certain kinds of measurements
and then it's in a strict quantum
theoretic formalism
time is not an observable
but distance is
so it's an observable like any other
so in a in a very strict sense
quantum theory is not a mechanical
theory because it's not really about
things going on in an independent
spacetime
[Music]
did you have a question
yeah i'd just like to
comment on and i say thanks for
referencing state spaces for systems i
think that's really helpful
because i um i've been wrestling with
this
dynamical part of systems which is
really helpful to think in dynamics but
most or a lot of people when they talk
about systems they just think about
relationships between things
and system dynamics i just flows as if
it's like things being passed around
rather than dynamical
like processes so i think it's helpful
to think about state space
in that way to frame systems and i'm
i'm just um
yeah i'm curious about how
we
have to be careful about people who use
systems in those other ways and don't
have a dynamical
uh
concept of something which is non-linear
being taken into account because
that seems to be something that this
approach really gives the ability to do
so i wonder what your thoughts are on
that
carl would you like to say something to
yeah i'm not sure it's going to be
deeply informed um so i'm i'm
as i'm listening i'm so trying to
translate all these beautiful ideas into
a classical framework that i'm much more
comfortable with so but the last point
is um
from the classical perspective
absolutely fundamental i mean you start
with a launch valve or a random
dynamical system that is just cast in
terms of flow operators or movement
operators that you can cathex with time
if you want to but just to reinforce um
chris's point you know time and space um
are both constructs and then you know
they're just explanations
for what well for these flow operators
so if those flow operators have a
dynamics
then implicitly you've got a rate of
change with respect to something which
is time but uh you know that's quite a
big move um
and um
[Music]
so
putting things in terms of mappings i
think is absolutely fundamental so steve
if your point was
when you need to think about
systemic
processes or systems from the point of
view of
mappings
usually associated some time i get the
impression from um
working with chris and jim that um
there is an ordinal or a sequential
aspect so just going back to the
question where did memory get into the
game you know that there has to be
um there has to you know there can still
be sequences or um your
sets of things um that has constitute a
memory but it doesn't have to have the
attribute of um of time in the sense
that we would understand a flow from the
point of view of a differential equation
so i'd like to hear that i'd like to
hear sort of um uh chris and jim's
comments on that
while i'm talking though it um
just this importance of um
time as a construct um it does strike me
that you know
that
takes um does a lot of heavy lifting if
we just abandon the notion of some
universal or clock time
in relation to what i would um
from a classical perspective
um read the scale free aspect of and i'm
thinking here of the renormalization
group
um i've been just to know that you know
and i'm sure there is if there is a
renormation group or the apparatus of
the removalization group in quantum
physics but from my perspective um
that
that notion of having a scale-free
approach is exactly
um
what is the
aspiration
of any
um
in particular the free energy principle
approach um would have
when trying to account for
the progressive
um
increase
in the scale of a system but preserving
exactly the same dynamics the same
lagrangians the same so again from a
classical perspective the same um the
same functional forms
for the the things that are concerned so
yep this is to reiterate chris's
fundamental point earlier on that and
we're not talking about um a commitment
to a particular scale be very very small
or very very big what we're talking
about it's a commitment to the same
functional forms and the apparatus and
the mathematics that underwrite the
the the dynamics if you like and that's
you're at any given scale and then that
calls then into question
how do you get from one scale to the
other
um and i'm
one thing that sort of
jumps out to you when you when you look
at the
the
renormalization group in relation to um
summarizing dynamics of random
differential
systems
is that you get this time dilation or
this you know you move from one tonight
skill to another time scale um so i'm
i'm coming back to the point that you
know when you talk about time what's
skateboard scale what time are you
talking about are you talking about
evolutionary time are you talking about
um
uh sort of you know
the time that um the fetus is enjoying
in its mother's womb or you're talking
about the time scale appropriate for the
the fluxes of ions over your
cell membrane um so the deeper question
here is that how does one temp one time
relate to another um the people that i
know who are
interested in this issue from the point
of view of
the perception of time or time as a
construct
um
usually fall back on information rates
they usually fall back on the
the rate of belief updating or the
amount to which you have moved in some
belief space technically
manifold
from a classical point of view but as
soon as you say weight
with respect to what
um and then it comes back with
some time which time
and where you end up
where you end up as well okay
um i can't talk about any absolute
information rate but i can certainly
talk about um
the number of moves i make at one scale
per number of moves i make at another
scale
even we could be doing that in our heads
you know when we
very high
scales say from the point of view of a
generative model in our in our heads
dealing
[Music]
with things that unfold
very slowly in relation to
fast move updating much closer say to
our sensory organs or
actuators um but it does make sense you
know to actually talk about how much
have i moved how far have i moved in
terms of an information length
in my belief updating
in um at a higher level of a hierarchy
or you know a higher scale
in relation to the to the number of
moons or how far i have moved
we've got somebody
okay okay or you can just
um
it'll be it'll be muted
my that little response was very
rambling because there are so many just
like questions come up over the past
10 20 minutes i i like to pass that to
to chris and jim now that i understood
um to get their take on um
how comfortable they would be by taking
the notions of um say the
renormalization group as applied to
pathogenic formulations of random
dynamical systems and whether that has
any homolog or any currency in a truly
background-free quantum population
well i don't know
well
um basically i i
think um what carl is
proposing concerning the renormalization
group and the van der waals theories um
something to be investigated
concerning
um
the
aspect of um
memory from the
informational point of view
and um may i speak
about the specifics of our construction
namely the
cone
cocoon diagram
which um
okay you could mute or just yeah
that's all good
we're going to be looking at the cone
cocoon
um
maybe just chris or carl you can give a
first
pass
like what is this being shown and also
how does it relate to active inference
oh hello
okay welcome back
uh local distraction
um
yes uh okay well uh you see
at the beginning of the paper when we
discuss discuss the
holographic screen which underlies the
markov blanket you have
these preparation
measurement operations which
feed
into the diagram
diagram 14
um
of which
the lower part emanating from d prime
is um
a
memory write system
so as the
um
the top part is picking up information
from
the measurement and preparation
operators
there is a memory rights system
being um
implemented
from the opposite
direction
um
one thing i i would like to say about
the individual classifiers that
we haven't sort of um
fully mentioned in the paper that an
individual classifier
uh can be the result of um an algebraic
operation on
on two other uh
classifiers
um
these algebraic operations
uh can be of the type such as
concurrency
or
ortho currents for example when you have
a system of trains going through a
system of stations
um
the
the classifiers in question
uh can be um
combined to that extent and also by
choice so i i think the scope for
what is happening informationally
in diagram 14 is uh quite significant
um
originally um two spaces were applied to
such areas
as
as as concurrency and
um
high dimensional
automata
um
and also um
we can look at the possible uh
possiblistic
uh
case
and
there are ways of interpreting diagram
14 in terms of the graph network too
so um
i know this doesn't exactly answer uh
carl's uh questions but um i i i want to
say that there is the mechanism there
um for the uh
memory right
so um
this is um of course uh influential when
uh you see that um
inference leads to
minimizing the
variational free energy principle
if you have any questions about those
diagrams please ask me
perhaps chris can elaborate on what i'm
saying
uh yeah let me make a background
comment here
uh
which in a sense goes to
uh one reason that we're using this
quantum theoretic formalism
if we
if we think of everything in terms of
a
a quantum theoretic formalism in turn
instead of a classical formalism
then
the only place that there's any
classical information in the system
is actually on the boundary between the
two interacting components
so
um
in that original i
i don't know whether it's figure one or
the
the the very original idea in the paper
is that we we have some
closed system which we can think of as
the universe as a whole or the universe
of interest as a whole
and
it's in some quantum state
and if we divide it into two and we make
the assumption that
the joint state after the division is
separable that we've divided it in a
place
where the interaction of the system with
itself is weak enough
that we can think of the two halves
independently of the two components
independently
then we have this natural sense of
classical information written on that
boundary and that's the sense of
classical information that one
encounters in the holographic principle
in cosmology
and
it's it's in that sense of classical
encoding
that
of this boundary serves as a markov
blanket
but since the boundary is the only locus
anywhere of classical information
in this formal description
then any classical memory has to be
resident on that boundary
and
this actually brings to mind a picture
which was not included in this paper
but that i'm using in a subsequent paper
with
mike levin
which really is is just thinking of this
boundary using a pie chart and
as we pointed out in this paper
uh
another kind of classical information is
the classical free energy flow
that powers information processing so
this this actually isn't the right
picture but
um
and
so one can immediately carve off a large
chunk of the boundary and say okay this
is just thermodynamic exchange these
bits aren't useful to anybody
they're
they're the bits that are being used
burned as power
yeah this is a better picture
for that
and then
there's a
chunk of the pie chart
that we can think of as perception and
another chunk of the pie chart that we
can think of as action
but then some other piece of the pie
chart has to be allocated to memory
or
there's no internal time
right having an internal clock
and having a memory are the same concept
if i don't have any memory at all then i
have no awareness of the passing of time
and i have no internal clock
so when jim talks about
uh in that
previous
cocon diagram
a memory right operation it's a memory
right operation on the boundary
and
of course the the opposite partner in
the interaction
uh my memory segment of the boundary
from my point of view
might be my partner's perception segment
of the boundary
or might overlap with my partner's
perception of the segment of the
boundary i have no idea how my
interaction partner cuts up the boundary
from their point of view
so
um
this is yeah that that's what this
picture sort of illustrates
uh
so this question of of
what is the memory
also becomes observer independent
which which gets back to this question
of time and the relationship of time to
a local clock and the relationship of a
local clock to memory
so whenever we talk about
time as observed by
someone
oh we're making reference to a local
clock and a memory resource and of
course an energy flow that powers that
memory resource and prevents it from
decaying
entropically so this i
we keep circling back to this
abstraction of the universal time that
parameterizes the universal dynamics
but um
and you know this this formalism like
any such formalism requires that concept
is a theoretical construct
but
at least it doesn't confuse it with the
the experienced time of any particular
observer which has to be represented in
this very different
in this very distinct way
awesome thanks so i think that is a
perfect segue
into a question that was asked by franz
kutzling in the live chat um and also
mike levin has joined us i don't know if
he's able to talk he says he's having
some internet issues mike did you want
to say hello before i asked franz's
question
if you can
be muted
um
okay i'll ask the question and then
we'll see if mike figures out how to
unmute and say hi
um so franz asks
how does the definition of a thing that
maintains its identity over time scale
with time scales or
over scale with time scales there you go
how does the definition of a thing that
maintains its identity over time scale
with time scales
what
i still didn't get it for example i
would call something a thing if it
persisted for some time
with respect to my observational time
scale so in other words can quantum
theory
say something about how to set temporal
observer limited boundaries of defining
a thing
there's a lot in there
yeah
um
we see many ways um some that are
actually
implicitly scale friendly or scale free
like the hierarchical parametric models
in spm statistical parametric modeling
that's separating like in a multi-scale
experimental design from an
experimentalist's perspective
into signal and noise including the
combinatoric interactions
in a classical parametric state space
and there's also um the
uh
bayesian identification
of parameters which also is
just as was brought up scale implies
choosing what the state space is
and so what
statistical variance gets partitioned
into the noise term or the kind of
ripple term and what gets partitioned
into the wave term into the signal into
the regression slope rather than the
variance term
these kinds of variance partitioning
questions
can be approached in a
instantaneous sense like descriptive
statistics even if it's about time
series
and um
i think
a theme that we're hearing brought up is
that taking repeated measurements
seriously
brings in a whole host of essentially
cognitive features
like
as well as
information theoretic
perspective dependence
all of these features
that are
um tucked under the rug or um down
projected onto in a special case
if we just assume a synchronous universe
um or a synchronous regression it's a
totally different scenario
but considering this quantum statistical
background
helps us
deal with the cognitive modeling and
also take the consequences of action
into account
because action is implied in the
measurement preparation
recording experimental active inference
cycle
it was just so subtle in the paper we
said all inference in this scheme is
active inference
but the paper was about quantum and the
fep
um
thanks
uh could i bounce off what daniel just
said very quickly
because uh i was also thinking about the
nature of action i thought i was um so i
thought what daniel just mentioned there
ties in with
is is if memory
happens via
there being some action and then the
action
defines the memory scale there's
um
so
i think that makes
that that that starts to define a scale
so i'm curious
that if if there's something different
between
the the temporality of a thing
maintaining its thinness
and
the sort of temporality of um
actions
by systems of things
because i think things can only act to
maintain their thinness but they don't
if they start doing things with others
they become a system so i suppose you've
got
where where that action still starts to
come into the equation or am i mistaken
there
can i address that briefly
yeah i i think a relevant the relevant
fable here is the
fable of the two drunks who are walking
home from the bar leaning on each other
and
if they're lucky they manage to keep
each other upright
if
if if we if we think
of
an observer in an environment
and so we draw a boundary between
the observer and the environment
and we think about the observer's
interaction with its total environment
then we've divided the boundary up as we
were talking about earlier
uh into a pie chart where
you know a large fraction of the bits
are fuel
and so they're
uninformative and there's a perception
space in an action space and a memory
space and so on
now let's think about what happens when
the observer identifies a thing
embedded in the environment
so the observer has now
segmented or sectored
the
the perception part of the space
into
a part
that
includes bits that represent the state
of this thing
and the rest of the perception space
which are bits that represent the
background
that the thing is embedded in so the
things environment
and so the question becomes what does it
mean
to say that that thing
remain
retains its thinness its identity over
time
for that observer
uh
well that means that
that observer
is able to
maintain this distinction
between
bits that communicate information about
the thing and bits that communicate
information about the thing's
environment
so this becomes a cognitive question
about the observer
so
it's
the question how does a thing
maintain its identity
is replaced in in this way by the
question
how does an observer of a thing
maintain the thing's identity
for
himself or for itself
how does the observer
uh
maintain the ability to lock in on this
thing is distinct from the environment
and
um
[Music]
so let's let's go to an example
right think about motor babbling in an
infant
so
here's this infant she's lying on her
back she's waving her arms and her legs
around
and
what she's doing in this motor babbling
is
figuring out the relationship between
the motor system and the visual system
so
among other things she's figuring out
that some that something that she sees
some visual stimulus
is actually part of her body it's a hand
and that at a certain moment she begins
to be able to control what this hand is
doing
uh
using visual and motor feedback
so here's here's a living example of an
observer
of
fixing the identity of an object
and what we're trying to do here in a
sense is
use this as a
is is to insist on thinking about
thinghood always in this observer
specific way
so i noticed that carl just raised his
hand so let me turn it over completely
to him to carry on with that or contest
it or give a different perspective
no i do i don't want to contest it i
want to fully endorse that and if you
just
look at the free energy principle as
classically formulated it is exactly uh
along the lines of
the uh the thickness being an attribute
of the observer so if you just start off
with the notion of a markov blanket that
stupidly defines a thickness how is the
markov blanket defined well it's defined
by the conditional independence between
the dynamics on the inside versus the
outside
but of course
those dynamics are not observable once
they're on the inside from the outside
by definition
so you're immediately
imputing
some magical
observer that could actually recognize
that independence before you've even
defined what a thing is so i just wanted
to to you know um
in an abstract and possibly even
philosophical way
and reinforce this notion that thingness
does you know is an attribute of
something that could possibly observe it
even from the classical perspective of
the free energy principle predicated on
the notion of a mark or blanket that is
in turn uh defined in terms of
conditional independences or
disentanglement um
but the the that example of the um
of motor babbling i think is that you
know again a lovely illustration of
um
observation
underwriting thingness and in this
instance um your highly
anthropomorphized thing that's name is
selfhood you know to to develop the
hypothesis or the explanation
for my holographic screen or my um
all the uh information on my markov
blanket that
a a
plausible parsimonious explanation is
that i am a thing i am a self i am me
is is actually you know takes months if
not years to fully actually uh you know
arrive at as you're an infant slowly
discovering that i am different from mom
and perhaps mom is different from the
background and
ultimately perhaps i am something like
mum uh so you know
these um the emergence of thingness i
think is it is quintessentially observer
dependent both mathematically and in
terms of developmental uh psychology
great thank you
oh crap did you want to head on sorry i
was trying
how lucky the technology
so
maybe i will put put this back to carl
maybe you were talking earlier
before jim started talking about the
rate of information flow
and the rate of belief updating
and so i just wonder i've been curious
about this actually um
just in terms of human
information like are we really bombarded
with more information now than we used
to be
um and is this like influencing our rate
of cultural change cultural evolution
because as a culture like we
update our beliefs more often do you
think that these two things are
proportional the rate of information
flow and the rate of belief updating
something i've been thinking about
yes no i i'm sure that's absolutely
right
and right i think you know at every
scale of analysis
um so you could look at it from the
point of view of culture and the
availability of information on social
media and globalization uh at a cultural
scale but you could also i think um
bring us back to motor bubbling that you
know the degree of bleep updating an
infant has to do
um
is clearly going to be much greater than
somebody um of of my age um
so you know time will
a year in the life of an infant will not
be the same as a year in the life in my
life and you know
i think that that is a direct reflection
of the degree of belief updating
interestingly that that question um
touches upon the separation of time
scales which i think underwrites
everything that we're talking about here
um
so
you just stand back again and go back to
some of uh chris's earlier observations
um about the
remit of
the um the paper in question
um it was really at any given but not
specified scale
um
where
we could assume that um
[Music]
we didn't have to worry about the
separation of time scales from the point
of view of a cognitive
neuroscientist for example what we're
talking about is inference where
inference in this instance would be read
as
um a kind of reading and writing onto
this holographic screen or if you're one
of the perspective um the you know the
updating of um active and sensory states
on the on the markov blanket um
but
under the assumption that the
the the
other things that change at a slower
time scale are not changing
and those other things might not be
might be for example at a slow time
scale they might be learning
so you've got this notion that the the
formalism at hand
the reading and writing at hand
from the
information theoretical perspective
could be a very good metaphor for
inference
you know over a short time period where
there um where things are not changing
very quickly from a point of view on the
things to be learned
so within a few seconds or minutes of
the life of the zygote
acknowledging that you could apply the
same apparatus and the same mechanics
at a slower time scale that would
account for the transition from a zygote
to a to a neonate as it learns so the
difference between inference and
learning i think is is
a nice
common sensible example of this
separation of time skills so when you
ask about you know cultural information
available i think you're probably
talking about
a scale of learning um and
absolutely you're
when we learn we update our beliefs
there it will be from a classical
perspective a statistical manifold that
holds those beliefs and you're literally
moving over that um and with respect to
another scale and then the degree of
belief update and the degree of asking
questions the degree of read writing um
will certainly be
be a function of the amount of reading
or writing that's going on and i can
imagine that somebody
somebody who has access to wikipedia or
news on social media is doing a lot more
read writing
than i was saying
in the 1960s
[Music]
okay you're moving but to me blue
yes to you
so
carl you made a fascinating point about
connecting the motor babbling and taking
it into the informational and the belief
updating domain um
into the adult
where we're kind of motor babbling on
social media in a way that has different
dynamics than before
um
and people often give the example of
like well a year feels longer for a
seven-year-old because it's the seventh
of their life but then for the 80 year
old it's an 80th of their life so that
piece of the pie is smaller versus
bigger
and that is implicitly the fallacy of
the observer independent time as if
there was a linear chart that was being
linearly divided by some static observer
whereas another way to look at that or
an alternative model is like the rate of
development or experiences or change or
novelty or
continue to explore and don't worry all
mute james
is that
oh he's muted on the live stream so it's
all those um
that uh rate of belief updating
could set that internal
kairos that biological time like that
biological information geometry
and so it connects the cognitive
sciences and also the statistical
perspectives that have been
discussed to this
time
question which as also brought up
earlier does so much work
in so-called dynamical modeling
and it just makes me think about how
there was a movement from the observer
independent
synchronous
into
the relativistic
which prepared and almost like prepared
the
partition
to exist
so that all these other domains
like the holographic principle could
come into play
so
my question for any of the authors is
where does the qrf come into play and
how does this relate to discussions of
pluralism and polycentrality
awesome question
jim did you
answer well
um i i wonder if you can bring up a
diagram there um in the paper
uh let's see
sure
yes it's diagram 34 well there
you have a configuration that
um relates the
qrf to the
cochlear cone diagrams and
we say here that
um
let's see
well here we focus on co deployable
observers uh when this
uh diagram uh commutes
um
it is interesting of course um when the
diagram doesn't commute and then you
have a kind of intrinsic
uh
context uh
reality
so
um
i i i think
what this is saying is that
um there are
there are certain elements of um
information represented by the logic of
the distributed system in question
that are
um
kind of uh ambiguous
or um
rather
they're manifest in um
classifiers and infomorphisms that
um
aren't defined or
um the co limit the bolt c at the top
there
uh does not exist
so um this is a very useful criteria uh
i think to
uh distinguish between sort of um
empirical models which the best part are
based on co-deployable variables and
what happens
when quantum
contextuality um occurs the that is
diagram 34
um doesn't uh commute so
there's some sort of
uh discrepancy there in the um
uh mechanism of the quantum reference
frame
um
relative to the dynamics of from
the markov blanket or the the
holographic screen
underlying it so
um
there is some kind of distortion in
meaning um
that results in this sort of intrinsic
contextuality
uh i i i don't know if that's a
satisfactory
uh answer at all
but um
when this breaks down i haven't seen
that before it sounds good
i'm sorry there's another local distress
it's all good
chris did you want to add on to that or
maybe make another comment
uh well i wanted to go back
a little bit to the basics of what a
quantum reference frame is because this
is a
concept that
is both very familiar and i think a
little bit unfamiliar
and the the term was
only coined
back in the 1990s
when
uh
the the idea of of
a quantum measurement
was associated with with the idea of
uh
the the units in which the measurement
is made and what are the requirements
for
a measurement being meaningful and we're
going to get right back to the same
issues we've been talking about with
respect to time and thingness
but
a a reference frame
is
just a way of giving meaning to an
outcome
and it's
it's what allows outcomes to be compared
so if i have an apparatus like a meter
stick
i can go around and measure
lengths
and as long as i believe that my meter
stick
maintains its identity
as long as i believe that my meter stick
remains the same thing
then i can compare the lengths that i've
measured
but if i don't believe my meter stick
remains the same thing
[Music]
uh then i then these length comparisons
are meaningless
so
the notion of of a reference frame is is
intimately tied up with this notion of
meaning
which in a
in this free energy principle context is
really a notion of actionability
uh can i use
what something means to guide my actions
and my decision-making
so
this notion of a qrf
becomes a notion of
giving
of
giving an outcome value that i obtain
and write in memory comparability with
other outcome values that i maintained
and write in memory
and we're very used to you know as human
beings we have this incredibly
complicated
sensory and inferential apparatus
that
involves many many degrees of freedom
and many many values that are
distinguishable so i think if we want to
think about something like
the role of of reference frames in
perception
it's it's better to think in terms of
something like e coli
oh
and
so think of a much simpler kind of
system that can measure fewer things
right e coli can measure concentrations
of salt and sugars of various kinds
and
those concentrations are meaningful to
it
those concentrations allow it to make
decisions
because its internal biochemistry
assigns them an actionable meaning
so
chemotaxis in e coli works
uh
because the
level of phosphorylation of a particular
chemical
remains reasonably constant that's the
reference frame
[Music]
and
concentration levels can be compared to
each other as long as that
phosphorylation state remains reasonably
constant that reference frame is
meaningful
and so chemotaxis makes sense
because e coli has if you will a slow
clock
how the phosphorylation state of chi y
uh that assigns that that confers
meanings upon its outcomes
so now we can spool back to what jim was
saying about co-deployable reference
frames of
reference frames
that i can use at the same time
[Music]
that i can
obtain information from simultaneously
have to commute
this is what heisenberg's uncertainty
principle is about
oh
and if i can't use them at the same time
it's because they don't commute if i use
them in different orders i get different
answers
and
what that means is that by switching
reference frames
i'm effectively changing
the
the calibration i'm effectively changing
the meaning
that i've
assigned and uh i think
a very beautiful place to see this uh is
the paper a paper that we reference here
uh from cervantes in zafra and zafrov
called the snow queen experiment
uh the paper's called uh snow queen is
evil and beautiful
i'll came out a few years ago
and
basically this paper is demonstrating
quantum contextuality and human decision
making
and it's doing it by exploiting
differences context dependent
differences in the meanings of words
so it's it's it's perfectly pointing out
this relationship between meaning
and co-deployability
and hints and hence context dependence
in human cognition so that's that's a
paper i'd very much recommend reading
thank you so much carl did you want to
comment on that also
yes
i'm aware that stephen also the question
but uh just to follow up on on
um that um
beautiful deconstruction um
[Music]
this is more of a question but i'm going
to state it as an observation um this
notion of
the qrf as being fundamentally getting
um
measurements right or metrics right
would be understood from the point of
view of
inference technically um
as getting um an internally consistent
metric
correct and the metric we're talking
about is a fisher
information metric so um you if you look
at all reading and writing or action and
sensation from a classical perspective
as just trying to minimize some
divergence or some prediction error
what you are saying is that you are
trying to find an internally consistent
metric in an information space
um that makes sense of your active
sampling querying the world
um so it just sounded to me as if what
chris was saying was exactly uh
getting the measure the measuring stick
at least behaving consistently you'll
never know whether it's changing its
length or not but at least if it behaves
consistently in relation to what you can
see of the world the way that you can
query that world actively then that's
good enough and that of course is is
um
one way of simply stating that the name
of the game in active imprints is just
to minimize your prediction error where
you are now reading prediction error
as a kl divergence and of course the
the information length or the amount the
measurement of movement the metric is
just a uh a path integral of
infinitesimal changes in kl divergence
so it's been from a mathematical
perspective on the perspective of
information geometries there's a
beautiful link here between aligning
your qrfs and getting your generative
models right to make the most sense in
the sense of minimizing or making as
internally consistent as possible all
your information metrics
awesome thank you
um before we go to stephen's question we
have a question or two from the from uh
ander aguirre in the live chat
he asks does the existence of a
holographic screen slash markup blanket
automatically yield a statistical
manifold for the belief state of the
agent
and is there a canonical renormalization
procedure for a quantum mechanical
system
if there is one how would the core
screening translate into the statistical
manifold
oh i i can take one
quack at that which is
uh
if i if i'm coarse graining something
[Music]
if if we think of this in terms of qrfs
uh
then i'm i'm deploying a different
reference frame with lower resolution
so
the
in a sense what's being renormalized
is
my representation
of the units
that i use to distinguish states of the
world
so
if if i have
a meter stick
uh
that's made of stainless steel
that has millimeters
indicated on it
then i can go around and make
measurements in millimeters
uh that if i coarse grain to a meter
stick
that only has half centimeters indicated
on it
uh then i've lost a factor of five in
resolution i've coarse grained by a
factor of five
and so i've i've in effect rounded off
all my outcome values
and now my my
function of comparing outcome values
is is differently defined
because it has to work at this lower
resolution
and if i want to
compare my previous values to my later
values
i have to incorporate this explicit
roundoff function into my comparison of
values because i've changed my qrf
so
coarse graining
which which of course couples to scale
changing
uh from the very beginning of our
conversation
can be thought of as a transition from
a
a very
a qrf with some grain size to a qrf for
a similar degree of freedom with a
different grain size
uh and that has ripple effects
uh
through everything including the
the free energy cost of memory
right if i'm if i'm writing
two-bit numbers into memory then that's
a lot less expensive than writing
five-bit numbers into memory
so
um
this raises the another aspect of this
question of renormalization which is
how does it influence
how can i use it
to
solve the trade-off problems
that arise if i'm an organism with a
limited fuel supply which of course i am
[Music]
of going about the world
trying to gather
uh
preferentially the gather the
information that's going to be most
useful to me at the lowest possible cost
so
again we get back to this
key
issue
uh in
in all of active inference of
balancing of
the risk of exploration against the
reward of new information
uh and coarse graining is is intimate to
that
and it involves the choice i make of the
tools that i'm going to use to make
measurements
and how that choice impacts
my need to allocate computational
resources and energy resources to what
i'm doing too
to the to the complex task of of getting
new information while at the same time
surviving
awesome thanks
daniel did you oh carl do you want to
speak to that first
perhaps stephen should ask but then i
can come back to what just said yeah
i'll um make a note and then carl would
be great to have your response and then
stephen's your question so to transpose
it into statistical parametric mapping
the true classics there's a mapping from
the measured voxels which are being
defined by the resolution of the eeg or
the fmri machine that's the holograph
that's like what the experimental
apparatus is providing is the
measurements those are the o
in our partially observable markov
decision process it's the predicted
value in the regression
and that space you know if it's 128
channels in the eeg and they're getting
this sampling rate that is the state
space that's being discussed and that's
being
transposed or mapped or connected to a
different statistical space with
different features
and rather than the voxels there's like
the mapping onto res else so carl that's
why i'd appreciate if this is um true or
not but those are the resolution
elements and that it can be like a
coarse graining and in that um stretch
meter stick
and different space
there's a lot more statistical inference
options available that are just not
accessible at all
from the um voxel
coarse graining which is noisier and
there's a signal enrichment in the
coarse graining to the results that's
appropriate and then that gets
juxtaposed with the contrasts which is
the experimental design of the
scientists like you couldn't
differentiate um a versus b category if
you only tested a so the experimental
design that's where like the statistics
actually comes into play
and then
um just as chris said there's the
organism with limited food supply and
then there's like the scientists with
limited
time attention computer storage
processor time
funding
maybe seven billion people like he just
there's plausibility and so that's where
this operational co-deployment
connects with experimental design
and so many of the patterns and
analogies exist in the purely classical
domain of the parametric statistics like
spm
in the classical physics and the flow
and the information flow area that's
coming into play and also these more
recent in quantum areas so carl would
love to hear your thoughts on that
yes of course i'm i'm mindful that
stephen's still great
but
um perhaps i'll i'll speak to that and
then um
uh stephen can i ask a question but i
think yes that i think
you know
these questions and daniel your
responses are touching uh chris's
attaching on something really
fundamental so just to um answer the
question from the point of view of
markov blankety yes it does
automatically yield a statistical
manifold or at least it looks as if
there is a statistical manifold um if
you can observe the uh the behavior of
the thing that you are observing um
[Music]
the second thing uh question um
which we've been focusing on and
the core screening i i i think that's a
really fundamental thing i would um
argue that not not to conflate too much
the notion of renormalization which
would be
i think um
more a question of how you get from one
scale to another scale
um with the notion of course grading
which is which could be read just simply
as a degree of quantization or choosing
the right resolution element the right
um course grading of a given qrf at any
given scale you could argue that you
could contextualize it but i think
there's a there's a more fundamental um
argument here um and that's um the
argument that there will be
from a statistical perspective an
optimal
core screening for any given um
holographic screen or exchange
over a markov blanket and that's the one
that
statistically maximizes the marginal
likelihood um
which you could if you like
relate to this sort of getting the
measurements as internally consistent as
possible maximizing the predictability
of the next measurement you make that
goes hand in hand with a maximization of
the marginal likelihood or a
minimization of the variational free
energy
that
is important to remember because the
marginal likelihood can always be
expressed as accuracy minus complexity
where complexity
scores the degrees of freedom you're
burning up if you remember about the uh
the the the
the bits on the on the holographic
screen you need energy um
um to um to
from a classical perspective represent
and what that translates to in a very
simple way in terms of probability
distributions and functionals
is in maximizing the marginal likelihood
or the evidence for your
aligned or model of the world you are to
maintain a certain degree of accuracy
trying to minimize complexity so you're
using as few degrees of freedom your
core screening to the extent you can get
away with while maintaining an accurate
account of the
um
of say the sensory states um or the
perceptual space on your holographic
screen
and
if you know um from the point of view of
active inference just think about well
what would that sort of accuracy and
complexity look like in terms of the
consequences of action you get exactly
what chris was talking about which was
the um the expected uh complexity um
being the risk usually and i mean risk
in the sense of an economist or basin
decision theorist it is literally
mathematically the same thing
the expected accuracy now becomes um
you're a sort of um
expected utility or the um
the um expected uh log evidence the
other the likelihood uh the expected
likelihood that you would um get if you
could if you committed to this kind of
course screening so this course grading
is absolutely fundamental it's really
interesting to go back to
um the
all the sources where where
the core screening uh starts to make a
difference and i'm thinking here coming
back to daniel's uh notion of resolution
elements you know you find this in sort
of vena filtering you find in the match
filtering theorem there is an optimal
level of smoothing or blurring
for any given kind of
data about which you want to make an
inference or you want to assimilate um
you see this um
in
formulations of universal computation
that themselves are based upon solemn of
induction that get you right back to
kamalgarh complexity and compressibility
so you see it in
the drive that underwrites all
formulations of universal computation
to maximize compression by minimizing
the complexity of your of your message
passing getting as efficient and as
simple as you can and of course this
best way to make your account as simple
as possible is to course grain it and i
think you also see it in
the sort of the different levels of
um
cognition in psychology and in
neurophysiology in the sense that
the higher level more efficient
ways in which we
align our qrfs or
optimize our generative models always
lead you to a very coarse grade
quantization of the world so for example
i
um represent i am sure in my brain and
some neural populations the fact that i
am in my study i do not represent that
in terms of
very fine grained xyz coordinates down
to the millimeter i represented no i'm
in my study i carve the world
at its joints and those joints
basically demarcate the the kind of
corresponding i bring to the bring to
the table there are all sorts of
arguments you can pursue here to to
vindicate this is the very existence of
receptive fields
tiling a censorium in a way that is
covered by discrete quantized receptive
fields tells you immediately that the
way that the brain represents stuff on
the inside the if you could look at it
through brain imaging
is in this quantized fashion this course
grained fashion and those that cause
grainness and the size the deployment
and the organization of those receptive
fields has been optimized at many
different temporal scales so
i just give you a few takes on course
grading or something absolutely
fundamental to the structure of a
generative model
or to the way that we um we align our
qrs to to make sense of
of of the stuff on the holographic
screen or at least when when we are
when we are reading from that and sense
making in that sense
great
thank you stephen did you want to ask
the question yeah thanks no this is
really cool um it was going to come back
a little bit to now in the past and um
the the idea that you mentioned about
the way that we interface
or the assumptions of the interface then
changes how we um
we resolve the thing and the background
situation situatedness of that thing so
and so it's like and so that could then
also
and this is the question in a way is how
can that also
because if the way that that thing and
the assumptions are made sets up
like the meaning for influence the
action policy selection
and the way things are thought about
how can that
itself change the way the brain
or the way that organisms look at the
what things are
for instance in
the modern world we do see everything as
things we carve things up we see things
as separate like an individual is
separate
whereas if you go back to sort of
indigenous approaches time for them was
cyclical or followed
the river going down a hill or so there
was a
there was a complexity focus in a way it
was almost like the mounting car
problem of
finding the landscape
of meaning rather than defining
the thing
and what it is and carving it so i'm
curious about is this how much is
the way that the the quantum reference
field
you know translated into thinking about
what that thing is
and how that you know compares to say
our western cognitive frames
which kind of
we measure everything because we can
because basically we can control our
environment so heavily we've we can make
things very accurate whereas in the past
it might have been you know the kalahari
bushmen or the people in the middle of
the amazon
that somehow go with the landscape of
complexity
so that the way that
that is understood is going to be
different so i'm just curious about
how you think about that ways of knowing
great question i wonder also if that
ties into um
the
individuality of of temporal scales like
you mentioned the the cyclical time and
um
back to franz's question maybe earlier
about um
how
and a thing
over time that stays a thing over time
scales with the scale of the time or
with the cyclical nature of the time or
it reminds me back of um when we had
chris and shawna here talking about like
flattening time maybe that was just
shanna's talk
but um yeah anyway i don't know do you
guys anybody have any
temporal comments
just that there's an analogy to the
synchronization of clocks which is a
huge part of computer science and of
quantum
and other areas that question of
synchronizing clocks
seems to have some relationship to
cognitive model
not naive
um
[Music]
congruence in terms of synchronization
but in terms of
like time zone coordination
so if we're in the same time zone then
there's a comparability but for
cognitive states
and so i think that will be something
awesome to explore
in
next week's session and of course
in the long run
about what that kind of
semantic and rhetorical and narrative
alignment that isn't congruence
but reflects
a broader frame
which actually the differences within
the frame
are
the search through that field
thanks uh
and in the interest of of temporal
comments i think um maybe does everyone
just want to go around and um you know
give a final thought and maybe
an idea of what
they would like to see in
next week's
discussion and we will start with
stephen
yeah thanks
lots of lots of interesting things i
suppose i'm yeah curious about this the
way that um
collapsing of
the quantum reference frame might
scale differently or might the
assumptions that lead to the collapse
could
inform
different scales of uh
interactions and mixing and blending of
the
behavior and uh
yeah
digesting a lot of stuff that's come up
so yeah thank you for
for the opportunity to talk to you
awesome
uh daniel anything you want to see
happened next week
we always think of the dot zero it's
kind of like dropping into the skate
park or the bathtub
um
and so that was like a microcosm of all
the threads that get brought
together and then in dot one i feel like
we opened up so many
areas of
possible connection
and
so i'll just look forward to the
second repeated measurement
of this semantic or
regime of attention space
and see how the continued interaction
and engagement
updates our generative model pass the
dot to even
awesome
carl or chris do you want to give a
thought about what you'd like to unpack
in the next discussion
should i go first well chris thinks of
something very common to say um
so it's probably all from from daniel to
a certain extent uh stephen's question
as well i'd like to hear about the
principle of unitarity
um
entanglement and um
its relationship to this notion of
synchronization and the mutual alignment
of qrfs between things that are coupled
so coming to
the
regimes of attention i i think that
could be a very transparent link there
in the sense that
contextualizing your qrf i think for a
cognitive neuroscientist would be
getting your intentional set right and
possibly an implicit course grading
that comes along with a particular
attentional set um
taking that that notion to
attending to others and
synchronizing and communicating and
living in a universe that is also
composed of things like me
um i think bring brings some fundamental
questions about
classically generalized synchronization
quantum theoretically entanglement and
enabling that entanglement in the right
kind of way um via aligning your qrs and
getting the course grading right
in sympathy with your partner so that
i'd like to hear about the principal
unitarity entanglement and how it
relates to classical notions of
communication mutual inference and
generalized synchrony
well thanks for stealing what i was
gonna say
um
i i was also gonna say um how the
there's one like the final concluding
part of the paper talks about how the
fep is asymptotically the principle of
unitarity and i i really would like to
dive into that more and maybe any
potential implications of that
and now chris gets the final and
cleverest word
uh okay this this won't be terribly
clever uh
what i was going to do
was to uh
recommend uh
a lovely paper by alexi grinbaum
that we refer to in this paper
and
the
the closing sentence of that paper is
that physics is really about languages
and i think this ties in nicely to some
of the issues that stephen was raising
in his last question which i found very
interesting
about
you know how how do conceptual schemes
evolve at the cultural level
and
i i i in hearing about uh
the the whole issue of reference frame
synchronization uh or or reference frame
alignment and how that relates to
entanglement
this this really is a question about
language
and
um
that that paper by alexei grinbaum i
think makes this point very very
beautifully
uh so that that would be a nice thing to
look at at some point
um
let's see this is
that's probably a newer paper by him
uh the one i was referring to is uh
titled something like uh how device-free
how device-independent methods change
the nature of physical theory or
something like that it was published in
uh
studies in history and philosophy of
science
2017 or something like that
okay anyway thank you very much for this
yeah this was um
very
interesting and engaging
and really appreciated everyone's
participation and blues facilitation
so we'll look forward to seeing anyone
just drop in or out when it works for
you
next week at the same time in number
40.2
so until the next measurement
thank you